William Allen Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William Allen Papers1796-1879 (bulk 1840-1876)
MSS10520
Allen, William, 1803-1879
3,000 items 23 containers 5 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, farmer, and U.S. representative and senator from and governor of Ohio. Correspondence, speeches, memoranda, financial records, printed material, maps, and other papers largely relating to Allen's service as United States senator (1837-1848) and governor (1873-1875) of Ohio.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Allen, William, 1803-1879.; Faran, James John, 1808-1892--Correspondence.; Graham, James, 1793-1851--Correspondence.; Hough, John, active 1831-1845--Correspondence.; Layman, Amos--Correspondence.; Morgan, George, 1777-1846--Correspondence.; Whitman, Henry A.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Ohio. Militia. Chillicothe Independent Blues.; Stoney Mill Salt Works.
Subjects
Greenbacks.; Mexican War, 1846-1848.; Oregon question.; Salt industry and trade--Ohio--Chillicothe.
Places
Northwest boundary of the United States.; Ohio--Politics and government--1787-1865.; Ohio--Surveys.; Oregon Territory--History.; Oregon--Boundaries.; Texas--Annexation to the United States.; United States--Politics and government--1815-1861.
Occupations
Farmers.; Governors--Ohio.; Lawyers.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Ohio.; Senators, U.S. Congress--Ohio.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of William Allen, lawyer, farmer, and politician, were purchased from Effie Allen Scott together with the
Duncan McArthur
Papers
in 1905.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William Allen are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1803, Dec. 27 Born, Edenton, N.C.
1819 Moved to Chillicothe, Ohio
1827 Admitted to Ohio bar
1833-1835 Member, United States House of Representatives
1837-1849 United States Senator
1849-1874 Resided on estate near Chillicothe, Ohio
1874-1876 Governor of Ohio
1879, July 11 Died, Chillicothe, Ohio
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Allen (1803-1879) span the years 1796-1879, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1840-1876. The collection focuses on his career in Ohio politics, first as United States representative and senator, then as governor of Ohio. Included are correspondence, speeches, memoranda, financial records, printed matter, maps, and other material. The papers are arranged in a bound Chronological File and a Miscellany.
The Chronological File consists primarily of correspondence, financial records, maps, and other material concerning Ohio and national politics during the 1840s and the 1870s. Topics include support of the United States annexation of Texas, the Mexican War, Oregon claims, land surveys, and the Greenback movement. Correspondents include James Faran, James Graham, John Hough, Amos Layman, George Morgan, and Henry A. Whitman.
The Miscellany consists of an account book of the Stoney Mill Salt Works, Chillicothe, Ohio, dating from 1811 to 1823, which Allen used partially as the backing for a scrapbook of clippings from 1825 to 1827. Also in the series are cancelled bank checks, an 1838 directory of the United States government, memoranda books containing jottings and accounting notes, newspaper clippings, a notebook, a promissory note, political literature, a scrapbook, speeches by Allen and others, and the records of the Chillicothe Independent Blues, an Ohio militia corps.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in two series:
Chronological File, 1825-1879
Miscellany, 1796-1877
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm75010520
Container List
- Chronological File, 1825-1879 (Box 1-21)
  Correspondence, speeches, memoranda, financial records, printed matter, and other papers largely related to Allen's career as a United States congressman (1833-1835) and senator (1837-1848) and governor of Ohio (1874-1876).
  Bound and arranged in chronological order.
  - 19 Apr. 1825-24 Sept. 1831 (Box 1)
  - 27 Sept. 1831-21 Jan. 1840 (Box 2)
  - 28 Jan. 1840-22 Jan. 1844 (Box 3)
  - 27 Jan.-28 Nov. 1844 (Box 4)
  - 29 Nov. 1844-12 Jan. 1845 (Box 5)
  - 13 Jan.-21 Feb. 1845 (Box 6)
  - 22 Feb.-29 Mar. 1845 (Box 7)
  - 30 Mar.-1 Dec. 1845 (Box 8)
  - 2 Dec. 1845-4 Jan. 1846 (Box 9)
  - 5 Jan.-1 Feb. 1846 (Box 10)
  - 2-27 Feb. 1846 (Box 11)
  - 28 Feb.-1 Apr. 1846 (Box 12)
  - 2 Apr.-21 May 1846 (Box 13)
  - 22 May-13 July 1846 (Box 14)
  - 16 July 1846-24 Jan. 1847 (Box 15)
  - 25 Jan. 1847-20 Mar. 1850 (Box 16)
  - 27 Mar. 1850-15 Oct. 1873 (Box 17)
  - 17 Oct. 1873-30 July 1875 (Box 18)
  - 31 July 1875-30 May 1879 (Box 19)
  - Undated (Box 20)
  - Undated (Box 21)
- Miscellany, 1796-1877 (Box 22-23)
  Account book, scrapbooks, memorandum books, notebooks, political literature, records of the Chillicothe Independent Blues Militia Corps, speeches, and other material.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by name of organization or type of material.
  - Bank checks, 1860-1873, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Chillicothe Independent Blues Militia Corps, records, 1821-1834
  - Memorandum books, 1854-1871, (3 folders)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1863-1876, undated
  - Notebook, 1845, undated (Box 23)
  - Political literature, 1823-1856
  - Printed matter, 1796, 1824
  - Promissory note, 1833
  - Scrapbook, undated
  - Speeches
    - By Allen, 1834-1876
    - By others, 1840-1877
  - Stoney Mill Salt Works, Chillicothe, Ohio, account book and scrapbook, 1811-1827
  - United States government directory, 1838